Finding Aid for Roscoe O. Bonisteel Papers 1903-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Roscoe O. Bonisteel Papers 1903-1972
Bonisteel, Roscoe O. (Roscoe Osmond), b. 1888.
Ann Arbor, Michigan, attorney, Republican regent of the University of Michigan. Correspondence and other materials relating to state and local Republican party affairs, particularly the election of 1944 and the Constitutional Convention, 1961-1962; organizational files, primarily concerning activities with the Rotary Club, the Free and Accepted Order of Masons, the National Music Camp at Interlochen, the American Bar Association, the First Presbyterian Church of Ann Arbor, the Historical Society of Michigan, Cleary College, Dickinson College in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, and the Wayne State University Board of Governors; and photographs.
85518 Aa 2
13 linear feet in 14 boxes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated in many installments beginning in 1944 by Roscoe O. Bonisteel (donor no. 2035 ) and later by Roscoe O. Bonisteel, Jr.
The collection is open for research.
Roscoe Osmond Bonisteel was born November 23, 1888 at Sidney Cross, Ontario. In 1891 he moved with his family to the United States. Following the retirement in 1913 of his father Milton F. Bonisteel from International Harvester the family moved to Ann Arbor, where Milton became active in both the real estate and the insurance business.
Roscoe Bonisteel received most of his early education in Pennsylvania, graduating from Harrisburg high school and receiving most of his undergraduate education at Dickinson College, Carlisle, Pennsylvania. Bonisteel received his college diploma, however, from the University of Michigan, which conferred upon him a bachelor of laws degree in 1912.
For the next half century Bonisteel practiced law in Ann Arbor. In addition to his practice, he was active in numerous professional organizations. He was president of the State Bar of Michigan (1936-1937), an organization he helped to create. He also served as a member of the American Bar Association House of Delegates (1936-1940).
Bonisteel's scope of activities, however, was far broader than his legal interests. He actively involved himself in politics, education, business, religion and community betterment.
Politically, Bonisteel was a conservative Republican. He served as an active party worker throughout his life. He was elected chairman of the Washtenaw County Republican organization and was appointed to numerous state boards and commissions. In both 1928 and 1944 he was selected as a delegate to the Republican National Convention. Bonisteel remained politically active throughout the 1950s. In 1961 he was elected as a Republican delegate to the state constitutional convention. At the convention he served on several committees, but was most influential in his posts as chairman of the education committee's sub-committee on higher education, and as vice-chairman of the committee on emerging problems. Education was a continuing concern of Bonisteel. He was a trustee of Dickinson College, a member of the Board of Trustees, Cleary College, the Board of Governors, Wayne State University (1956-1959) and the Board of Regents, the University of Michigan (1946-1959). In addition he served on the Board of Directors and was chairman of the executive committee of the National Music Camp at Interlochen.
In the business community, Bonisteel served as legal counsel for numerous corporate clients. Personally, he was a member of several Michigan firms' board of directors, including Ann Arbor Bank, Information Industry Associates, Michigan Life Insurance, and the State Bank of Frankfort.
Bonisteel worshipped at First Presbyterian Church of Ann Arbor. He was an active member of the congregation. He served both as an elder and a trustee of the church. In addition to all his other activities, Bonisteel was involved in a host of community organizations. He was a Mason, an active 33rd degree member, and a Michigan grand master (1929-1930). He was a Rotarian, serving that organization as president of the Ann Arbor chapter (1932-1933) and as International District governor (1934-1935). He was a member of the American Legion, having been a captain in the U.S. Air Service (area intelligence) during World War I. He was elected commander of Legion post 46 (1925) and served as judge advocate for Michigan (1934-1935). He was also active in historical organizations, most prominently as president of the Historical Society of Michigan (1961-1962).
Roscoe Bonisteel died on February 25, 1972.
The Roscoe Bonisteel collection dates largely after 1950, when Bonisteel had already reached an age at which most men retire. Because of this, many of Bonisteel's activities are either poorly documented or altogether absent from his papers. Despite this, the papers do contain some illuminating material.
The collection is divided into ten series: biographical and personal, colleges and universities, financial, historical organizations, legal, Masons, political, Presbyterian Church, Rotary, and Photographs.
Subjects:
American Bar Association.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Bonisteel, Roscoe O. (Roscoe Osmond), b. 1888.; Cleary College (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Dickinson College.; Elections--Michigan--1944.; First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Freemasonry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Historical Society of Michigan (1874- ); Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); National Music Camp.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Republican Party (Mich.); University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; Wayne State University.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Bonisteel family.; Bonisteel, Roscoe O. (Roscoe Osmond), b. 1888.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Cleary College (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Dickinson College.; Families.; Freemasonry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Leisure.; National Music Camp.; Rites and ceremonies.; Travel.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Commencements--1964.; University of Michigan. Law School--Alumni.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical and personal
  The biographical and personal material within the collection includes biographical and genealogical material, personal correspondence and a few items of sentimental value. The correspondence is truly personal, often with family members or close friends reporting on matters of family interest. A bound set of Bonisteel's diary, "From Day to Day," covering the years 1918 to 1971, is located in Box 14.
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - Awards and citations (Box 1)
    see also oversize folder
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Diaries
    - Handwritten 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Bound 1918-1971 (Box 14)
  - Annotated appointment calendars 1931, 1933, 1938, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Autograph book (Box 1)
  - "The Bonisink Saga," 1950 (Box 1)
  - Genealogical information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1938-1971, 21 folders (Box 1)
  - American Legion (Box 1)
- Colleges and universities
  Material about Cleary and Dickinson colleges, Wayne State University and the University of Michigan are all found under the heading, "Colleges and Universities". Material about either Wayne State or Cleary is thin. Because of his generous financial support of Dickinson, Bonisteel's correspondence with that school's officials is large. Most of it, however, tends to be progress reports on projects Bonisteel funded or gracious acknowledgments of his gifts. Some scattered minutes of the Dickinson Board of Trustees survive. The largest group of college material in the papers relates to the University of Michigan. The material is arranged alphabetically. Most of it dates from Bonisteel's appointment as a university regent to his death. While it is frequently said that Bonisteel was the "father" of U-M's North Campus, the papers are silent on the subject.
  - Cleary College
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    - Undated 1946-1972, 11 folders (Box 2)
  - Dickinson College
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (general) 1940-1971, 20 folders (Box 2)
    - Minutes, Board of Trustees 1959-1972, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Planetarium (donation of) (Box 2)
    - Portrait of Robert J. McClelland (Box 2)
    - Sandburg collection (donation of) (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan
    - Alumni Fund (Box 2)
    - Appointment of Bonisteel to Board of Regents (Box 2)
    - Association of Governing Boards (Box 2)
    - Class Reunions (Law 1912) (Box 2)
    - Commencement (honorary LLD, Bonisteel) 1964 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1961-1971 (Box 2)
    - Decision not to seek re-election to Board of Regents (Box 2)
    - Fairlane Festival, U-M Dearborn (Box 2)
    - Fundraising ($55 million program) (Box 2)
    - Harlan Hatcher, selection of (Box 3)
    - Inglis Estate (Box 3)
    - Investment/Endowments
      - 1952-1956 (Box 3)
      - 1958 (Box 3)
      - Butterfield Theatres, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Labor relations (Box 3)
    - Law School (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Monteith, John (Box 3)
    - National Music Camp (Interlochen)
      - History/Program (Box 3)
      - 1955-1967, 11 folders (Box 3)
      - 1968-1972, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Unidentified tape recording (Box 4)
    - Off-campus programs (Box 4)
    - Phoenix Project (Box 4)
    - Michigan State College name change (Box 4)
    - President (Box 4)
    - Rackham fund (Box 4)
    - Regent's correspondence 1947-1960, 14 folders (Box 4)
    - Scholarship Fund for Oriental Men (Box 4)
    - Speeches (Box 4)
    - Ten Hoor, Martin (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Club (Box 4)
    - University Musical Society (Box 4)
    - Veterans Hospital (Box 4)
    - Wayne State University (Box 4)
    - Workers Extension Service (Box 4)
- Financial
  - Ann Arbor Bank (Box 5)
  - Information Industry Associates (Box 5)
  - Michigan Life Insurance (Box 5)
  - State Bank of Frankfort (Box 5)
- Historical Organizations
  Historical organizations represented in the collection include the Ann Arbor Historical Commission, Ann Arbor Lincoln Sesquicentennial Committee, Clements Library, the Historical Society of Michigan, the Michigan Historical Collections and the Washtenaw Historical Society. There are also folders relating to biographical research on John Monteith and Gabriel Richard. Most extensive are papers relating to the Historical Society of Michigan. Also of interest is material relating to the Michigan Historical Collections, dealing primarily with the fund raising effort climaxed by the construction of the Bentley Historical Library.
  - Ann Arbor Historical Commission 1964-1969, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Lincoln Sesquicentennial Committee (Box 5)
  - Clements Library 1953-1972, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Michigan 1955-1971, 20 folders (Box 5)
  - Michigan Historical Collection 1946-1971, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Research Subjects
    - John Monteith, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Gabriel Richard, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Washtenaw Historical Society (Box 6)
- Legal
  Under the heading of "legal" are papers relating to Bonisteel's professional affiliations. Primarily, the material discusses the American Bar Association. There are only scattered documents regarding the Michigan Bar, or its predecessor organization.
  - American Bar Association
    - General (Box 6)
    - Committee on Admission to American Bar Association (Box 6)
    - Committee on Integrated State Bar Administration 1937-1946, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Committee on State Legislation (Box 6)
    - Section on Bar Organization Activities (Box 6)
    - Housing of Delegates (Box 6)
  - American Judicature Society (Box 6)
  - Michigan State Bar, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Uniform Laws Conference, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Washtenaw County Bar (Box 6)
- Masons
  Bonisteel's Masonic material is extensive. It is arranged into two groups, a general series and a second set of papers arranged alphabetically by committee. Among the committees Bonisteel served on are Constitutional, Education, Emerging Problems, Fead Memorial Fund, Jurisprudence, and Library and Museum. Also included is information regarding a controversy over the Prince Hall Lodge, a black Masonic affiliate.
  - General
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 6)
    - Undated (Box 6)
    - "Michigan Masonic Monitor and Ceremonies" circa 1877 (Box 6)
    - 1923-1953, 21 folders (Box 6)
    - 1954-1972, 17 folders (Box 7)
    - Constitutional Committee 1966-1971, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Education Commission 1924-1930 (Box 7)
    - Emerging problems (Box 7)
    - Fead Memorial Fund (Box 7)
    - Jurisprudence Committee 1940-1965, 15 folders (Box 7)
    - Jurisprudence Committee 1966-1970, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Library and Museum 1969-1971, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - William D. Greene/Prince Hall Lodge (black affiliate) (Box 8)
- Political
  The political material is also extensive. Included are the papers relating to Bonisteel's service at the state constitutional convention. In addition to the constitutional convention, the political papers are particularly informative regarding the 1944 National Republican convention and campaign and the unsuccessful effort of Frederick Matthei to win election to Bonisteel's seat on the University of Michigan Board of Regents in 1959.
  - General
    - Undated (Box 8)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 8)
    - 1913-1929 (Box 8)
    - 1930-1933 (Box 8)
    - 1934 (Box 8)
    - 1935-1939 (Box 8)
    - 1940
      - Correspondence (Box 8)
      - Vandenberg for president (Box 8)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 8)
    - 1943 (Box 8)
    - 1944
      - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Bricker for president (Box 8)
      - Dewey for president (Box 8)
      - Stassen for president (Box 8)
      - Martin/Taft for president (Box 8)
      - Presidential miscellaneous (Box 8)
      - Michigan campaign material (Box 8)
      - Michigan Republican State Central Committees Speakers' Manual (Box 8)
    - 1945 (Box 8)
    - 1946 (Box 8)
    - 1947 (Box 8)
    - 1948
      - Dewey for president (Box 8)
      - Stassen for president (Box 8)
      - Taft for president (Box 8)
      - Presidential miscellaneous (Box 8)
      - Michigan (Box 8)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 8)
    - 1951-1958 (Box 8)
    - 1959
      - Correspondence (Box 8)
      - Frederick Matthei (candidate for U-M Board of Regents) (Box 8)
    - 1960-1967, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Michigan Constitutional Convention Campaign
    - Correspondence February-September 1961, undated, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Lists of supporters (Box 8)
    - Campaign material, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Election results (Box 8)
  - Michigan Constitutional Convention
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 8)
    - Notes (handwritten) (Box 8)
    - Correspondence
      - September-December 1961, 4 folders (Box 8)
      - January 1962-1964, 12 folders (Box 9)
      - re: education (Box 9)
    - Civil Rights (Box 9)
    - Education Committee (Box 9)
    - Higher Education sub-committee, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - School revenues (Box 9)
    - Emerging problems (committee on) (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
- Presbyterian Church (primarily First Presbyterian of Ann Arbor)
  As an active member of First Presbyterian church of Ann Arbor, Bonisteel retained a great number of church related documents. Most interesting are four folders from 1933 and 1934 regarding the selection of a new pastor to lead the congregation.
  - Undated (Box 9)
  - 1903-1932 (Box 9)
  - 1933, 2 folders (Box 9)
    (largely re. selection of new pastor)
  - 1934, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1938-1959, 13 folders (Box 9)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 10)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 11)
    (continued)
  - Sermons and lectures, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Sermons and lectures, 4 folders (Box 11)
- Rotary
  The Rotary papers are most extensive for the years of Bonisteel's peak involvement.
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 10)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 11)
  - Undated 1916-1970 1934-1935, 55 folders (Box 10)
  - Undated 1916-1970 1934-1935, 55 folders (Box 11)
  - Speeches, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Speeches, 4 folders (Box 11)
- Photographs
  The Bonisteel photographs fall into three main series: Personal Photographs, College and University Photographs, and Topical File Photographs. Personal Photographs include several portraits, photos of family members, and photographs of friends and associates. College and University Photographs contain material from ceremonies and commencements at Cleary College, Dickinson College, and the University of Michigan. Two albums, one within the collection and another oversized album stored elsewhere, pertain to ceremonies at Dickinson College. In the Topical File subseries are photographs relating to various interests including: American Legion, Masons, and Bonisteel's many travels abroad.
  The Bonisteel photographs are most extensive for his involvement with educational concerns. Personal material is limited, yet this collection illustrates the many interests and activities of a prominent Michigan figure.
  - Personal Photographs
    - Portraits, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Early years (Box 12)
      (see also oversize photographs in box 13)
    - Law School graduation 1912 (Box 12)
    - Bonisteel (Mrs.) (Box 12)
    - Foster children (?) (Box 12)
    - Family
      - Groups (some color) (Box 12)
      - Individuals (female) (Box 12)
      - Individuals (male) and infants, some color) (Box 12)
      - Snapshots (Box 12)
    - Friends and relatives (Box 12)
    - Associates, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - College and University photographs
    - Cleary College
      - Commencement June 18, 1960 (Box 12)
      - Ceremonies 1961, 1969 (Box 12)
      - Building dedication May 1970 (Box 12)
    - Dickinson College
      - Commencements and reunions (with Mrs. Bonisteel and Professor Henry Yeagley) (Box 12)
      - Dedication of Roscoe O. Bonisteel, Planetarium November 11, 1958, album (Box 12)
    - University of Michigan
      - Ceremonies (Box 12)
      - Commencement 1964 (Box 12)
      - Commencements, 2 folders (Box 12)
        (includes President Johnson and George Romney photographs)
      - Honorary degrees (Box 12)
      - Interlochen, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Monteith, John (marker dedication) (Box 12)
      - Phoenix Memorial (Box 12)
      - Reunion (Box 12)
      - Travels (Box 12)
      - William L. Clements Library (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 12)
        (includes Hutchins, Button, and Angell photographs)
  - Topical
    - American Legion (Box 12)
    - Legal profession (Box 12)
      (see also oversize in box 13)
    - Masons
      - Ceremonies 1930 (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - Military ceremonies (Box 12)
    - Ten Hoor, Dan Martin (dinner in Tuscaloosa, Alabama) May 12, 1960 (Box 12)
    - Travels
      - Hong Kong (Box 12)
      - Philippines (Box 12)
      - Waseda University, Japan (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)